Pearson, Eliphalet, 1752-1826. Records compiled by Eliphalet Pearson relating to the election of Henry Ware as Hollis Professor of Divinity, 1804-1808 and undated: an inventory
Records compiled by Eliphalet Pearson relating to the election of Henry Ware as Hollis Professor of Divinity, 1804-1808 and undated.
Harvard University Archives
UAI 15.955
Pearson, Eliphalet, 1752-1826.
.22 cubic feet (1 legal half-document box)
This collection documents the involvement of Eliphalet Pearson, Hancock Professor of Hebrew and Other Oriental Languages and the College's interim President from 1804 to 1806, in the selection of the Hollis Professor of Divinity in 1805 at Harvard. Correspondence from New England ministers supports Pearson's desire to elect an orthodox Calvinist as Hollis Professor of Divinity, a narrative written by Pearson defends the selection of a Calvinist as Divinity Professor, and nomination slips and ballots provide evidence of the voting preferences of the Fellows of the Harvard Corporation. Additional records contain the questions Pearson used to challenge the election of Henry Ware as Hollis Professor of Divinity, extracts taken from the Massachusetts General Court Acts of 1642, 1650, and 1657 and the Harvard Corporation records used in Pearson's research during the selection process, a draft of a broadside focusing on theology, and Henry Ware's course of reading for divinity students at Harvard.
This document last updated 2011 October 20.
Acquisition information
The complete provenance of these records is unknown. Many of the records presumably were created in the course of University business and may have remained at Harvard after Eliphalet Pearson resigned his professorship and Corporation membership in 1806. Many of the records are marked with a handwritten note "Pearson papers."
Researcher Access
Records compiled by Eliphalet Pearson relating to the election of Henry Ware as Hollis Professor of Divinity, are open for research. Access to fragile original documents may be restricted. Please consult the Public Services staff for further details.
In the Harvard University Archives
Papers of Eliphalet Pearson, 1752-1826 (HUM 79): this collection contains a note regarding the selection of a new Hollis Professor of Divinity and an extract of a letter describing one of the candidates, Rev. Jesse Appleton.
Papers of Henry Ware, Sr., 1783-1842 (HUG 1871): this collection contains materials Ware created over more than half a century beginning as a Harvard undergraduate in 1785, a minister in Hingham, Mass., and later as the Hollis Professor of Divinity.
The Rules, Orders, and Statutes relating to the Professor of Divinity in Harvard College, at Cambridge, in New England, can be found in Rules and Statutes of the Professorships in the University at Cambridge, 1846 (HUC 4000.46.78).
Arrangement
The records are arranged in seven series:
Series I. Correspondence, 1804-1805
Series II. Intended publication relative to choice of Professor of Divinity, 1805
Series III. Nomination slips and ballots, 1804-1805
Series IV. Questions to be proposed to Overseers at meeting to confirm the choice of Mr. Ware, [1805 February 14]
Series V. Extracts from college and government records, undated
Series VI. Theses Theologica, first draft, [1805]
Series VII. Dr. Ware's course of reading for a student in divinity, 1808 September 2
Historical Note on Eliphalet Pearson
Eliphalet Pearson (1752-1826), scholar and the first principal of Phillips Academy in Andover, Massachusetts, served as Hancock Professor of Hebrew and other Oriental Languages from 1786 to 1806; Fellow of the Harvard Corporation from 1800 to 1806; and Acting President of Harvard University from 1804 to 1806. Pearson was an influential figure at Harvard as a professor and a contributor to many Harvard committees. After the death of Harvard President Joseph Willard (1738-1804) in September 1804, Pearson, an orthodox Calvinist, assumed the duties as president and soon became embroiled in controversy with other Corporation members regarding the election of Henry Ware (1764-1845), a Unitarian Congregationalist, as Hollis Professor of Divinity. Disenchanted with Harvard's increasingly Unitarianism and the election of Henry Ware as Hollis Professor in 1805, Pearson left Harvard and returned to Andover, Massachusetts, to help establish the Andover Theological Seminary in 1808. At the Seminary, Pearson served as professor of sacred theology (1808-1809) and as president of the board of trustees (1802-1821).
Historical Note on the election of Henry Ware as Hollis Professor of Divinity
After the death of David Tappan (1752-1803), the third Hollis Professor of Divinity, on August 27, 1803, efforts to appoint a replacement by the Harvard Corporation stalled over the religious beliefs the next Hollis Professor should hold. The Reverend Henry Ware (1764-1845), a Unitarian Congregationalist, was supported by the laymen members of the Corporation. However, Eliphalet Pearson (1752-1826), Hancock of Professor of Hebrew and other Oriental Languages, argued that the statutes of the Hollis Professorship of Divinity required that the Divinity Professor be a Calvinist, and Pearson opposed every candidate proposed that did not meet this religious qualification. Ware's supporters replied that requiring a religious test for a professorial candidate was a "barbarous relic of Inquisitorial power" and contrary to the spirit of the government and people.
President Joseph Willard died on September 25, 1804, before a successor to Tappan could be named. As the senior member on the Harvard faculty, Pearson was appointed acting president and soon after the election process for both the president and Hollis professorship began. Pearson supported the Reverend Jesse Appleton (1772-1819), a leader of the conservative element of the Congregational churches for the Divinity Professorship. The Corporation was equally divided and spent the month of December 1804 debating the merits of various candidates. On February 1, 1805, a compromise was proposed that would have Ware elected president of Harvard and Appleton as Hollis professor. After several trial ballots, Ware was nominated for the Hollis professorship by a single vote. On February 14, 1805, the Board of Overseers elected Ware as the new Hollis Professor of Divinity, and thus the oldest theological professorship in the country became Unitarian. The professorship controversy created a divide between Pearson and the liberal members of the Corporation and diminished Pearson's chances to be elected Harvard's next president. On December 11, 1805, the Corporation elected Fisher Ames (1758-1808), the Federalist statesman, as president of Harvard. However, citing poor health and old age, Ames declined the appointment. On March 1, 1806, Pearson resigned both his chair and fellowship at Harvard when it became apparent to him that he would not be selected as the next Harvard president. On March 3, 1806, the Corporation elected the Reverend Samuel Webber (1759-1810), Hollis Professor of Mathematics and Natural Philosophy and a Unitarian, President of Harvard University.
Historical Note on the Hollis Professorship of Divinity
The Hollis Professorship of Divinity was founded in 1721 by Thomas Hollis (1659-1731), a London merchant and one of the earliest supporters of Harvard College. It is the oldest endowed chair in the United States and the first professorship in theology in the country. The previous holders of the Hollis Professorship of Divinity were Edward Wigglesworth (1721-1765), Edward Wigglesworth (1765-1794), and David Tappan (1792-1803).
References
Bentinck-Smith, William and Elizabeth Stouffer. "Hollis Professorship of Divinity, 1721." In Harvard University, History of Named Chairs: Sketches of Donors and Donations. Cambridge, Massachusetts: Secretary to the University, 1991.
Fuess, Claude M. "Pearson, Eliphalet." Dictionary of American Biography. Ed. Dumas Malone, Vol. XIV. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1943. 358.
Morison, Samuel Eliot. Three Centuries of Harvard, 1636-1936. Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard University Press, 1936.
Quincy, Josiah. The History of Harvard University. Vol. II. Cambridge, Massachusetts: John Owen, 1840.
Wright, Conrad. "The Election of Henry Ware: Two Contemporary Accounts, Edited with Commentary." Harvard Library Bulletin 17 (July 1969): 245-278.
Scope and Content
This collection documents the involvement of Eliphalet Pearson, Hancock Professor of Hebrew and Other Oriental Languages and the College's interim President from 1804 to 1806, in the selection of the Hollis Professor of Divinity in 1805 at Harvard. The collection contains correspondence from New England ministers supporting Pearson's desire to elect an orthodox Calvinist as Hollis Professor of Divinity, a narrative written by Pearson defending the selection of a theologically "sound and orthodox" individual for Divinity Professor, and nomination slips and ballots which provide evidence of the voting preferences of the Fellows of the Harvard Corporation and also highlight the difficulties in selecting a new professor. In addition, the records contain the questions Pearson presented at a meeting of the Board of Overseers on February 14, 1805 to challenge the election of Henry Ware as Hollis Professor of Divinity and extracts, probably used in Pearson's research during the selection process, taken from the Massachusetts General Court Acts of 1642, 1650, and 1657 and Harvard Corporation records pertaining to Harvard College and the Divinity Professorship. Additional records include a draft of a broadside, Theses Theologica, focusing on theology, and Ware's course of reading (1808) illustrating the religious instruction given to students of divinity at Harvard at the beginning of the nineteenth century. The records demonstrate Harvard's movement away from orthodox Calvinism to the more liberal theology of Unitarianism and the controversial rejection of Pearson himself as a candidate for the Harvard presidency.
The records were assembled as an archival collection by the archivist at an unknown date from various sources without regard to original provenance in order to document University professorships.
Series Descriptions and Folder Lists
- I. Correspondence, 1804-1805; (4 folders)
  The correspondence in this series is arranged chronologically.
  This series consists of incoming correspondence written to Eliphalet Pearson pertaining to the appointment of Henry Ware as Hollis Professor of Divinity. The letters, written by ministers in New England, largely support Pearson's desire to elect an orthodox Calvinist as Hollis Professor. An unknown correspondent warns Pearson that the selection of a Unitarian as Hollis Professor would be disastrous to Harvard University and to the "interests of religion" while Jonathan Hayward explains to Pearson that parents will not send their children to Harvard if the University does not select a Calvinist who upholds the Assembly of Westminster and the 39 Articles of the Church of England.
  - Unknown correspondent to Eliphalet Pearson, 1804 December 22; UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 1
    The author's name in this letter has been crossed out.
  - [Jonathan] Hayward to Eliphalet Pearson, 1804 December 22; UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 2
    Jonathan Hayward (1739/40-1812) received his Bachelor of Arts from Harvard in 1756. He preached at Woodstock, Connecticut from 1760 to 1763. He later lived in northern New York for several years before moving to Woburn, Massachusetts.
  - Simeon Williams to Eliphalet Pearson, 1805 January 15; UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 3
    Simeon Williams (1743-1819) was pastor of the Second Congregational Church at Weymouth, Massachusetts.
  - Joseph Dana to Eliphalet Pearson, 1805 January 26; UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 4
    Joseph Dana (1742-1827) was a minister of the South Society of Ipswich at Ipswich, Massachusetts.
- II. Intended publication relative to choice of Professor of Divinity, 1805; (2 folders)
  Pearson's narrative is reproduced in Conrad Wright's The Election of Henry Ware: Two Contemporary Accounts, pp. 264-278.
  This series contains a narrative account written by Pearson defending the orthodox position at Harvard University. Pearson's narrative was never published and is dated before the vote for the president of Harvard and the Hollis Professor of Divinity takes place on February 1, 1805. In this narrative, Pearson criticizes the "time, manner, and unfairness" of the attacks made on the Corporation's selection committee beginning in the Columbian Centinel in September 1804 and continuing for the rest of the year; states that the three previous Divinity Professors were Calvinists and that the Corporation had an obligation to continue to select professors who were attached to "sound and orthodox" principles; and defends the orthodox position by declaring that the "real state of the controversy" revolves around those "who reject the religion of Jesus Christ and who support rational as opposed to evangelical religion, which was contrary to the religious sentiments of the University, its Founders, and Thomas Hollis."
  - Intended publication relative to choice of Professor of Divinity, first draft, 1805 January; UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 5
  - Intended publication relative to choice of Professor of Divinity, fair copy, 1805 January; UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 6
- III. Nomination slips and ballots, 1804-1805; (3 folders)
  The nomination slips and ballots in this series are arranged chronologically.
  The nomination slips and ballots in this series document the votes taken by the Fellows of the Harvard Corporation for the Hollis Professor of Divinity and the President of Harvard College. As Conrad Wright has written in The Election of Henry Ware: Two Contemporary Accounts, the slips provide "evidence as to the preferences of each of the Fellows." The slips also illustrate the tension between opposing religious views at Harvard at the turn of the nineteenth century, the attempts at compromise, and the difficulties in the selection of a Hollis Professor of Divinity.
  - Votes for nomination of a professor, 1804 December 15 or 26; UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 7
    Reproduced nomination slips and the votes of each Fellow can be found in The Election of Henry Ware: Two Contemporary Accounts, by Conrad Wright, figures 2-14.
    These nomination slips document the vote taken for Hollis Professor of Divinity by the Fellows of the Harvard Corporation on either December 15 or 26. The slips are not dated and it cannot be determined at which meeting they were used. This folder contains the nomination slips of Fellows Ebenezer Storer (1730-1807), Dr. John Lathrop (1740-1816), Judge Oliver Wendell (1733–1818), Eliphalet Pearson (1752-1826), Judge John Davis (1761-1847), and Dr. John Eliot (1754-1813).
    According to Wright, a meeting was held by the Fellows of the Harvard Corporation on either December 15 or 26 to vote for a Hollis Professor of Divinity. Each Fellow wrote the names of two candidates for the professorship. A stalemate developed and no final selection was made.
  - Trial votes for president and professor, 1805 February 1; UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 8
    Reproduced trial votes of each Fellow can be found in The Election of Henry Ware: Two Contemporary Accounts by Conrad Wright, figures 15-20.
    This folder contains the trial ballots of Fellows John Eliot, Judge John Davis, Judge Oliver Wendell, Eliphalet Pearson, and Dr. John Lathrop. According to Wright, five of the six trial ballots remaining reveal that the compromise failed by the narrowest margins.
  - Votes to elect a president, 1805 December 11; UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 9
    The ballots in this folder document the election of Fisher Ames as president of Harvard on December 11, 1805. Each of the ballots lists four names. The ballots are unidentifiable.
- IV. Questions to be proposed to Overseers at meeting to confirm the choice of Mr. Ware, [1805 February 14]; UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 10; (1 folder)
  The questions outlined in this series were used by Pearson to challenge the religious principles and qualifications of Henry Ware in his remarks to the Board of Overseers when he opposed the election of Ware to the Hollis Professorship of Divinity on February 14, 1805.
- V. Extracts from college and government records, undated, (5 folders)
  The extracts in this series are arranged chronologically.
  This series contains extracts taken from the Massachusetts General Court Acts of 1642, 1650, and 1657, pertaining to Harvard College, and extracts from 1721 to 1765 from Harvard Corporation records. They were probably used by Pearson in his research to challenge the election of Henry Ware as Hollis Professor of Divinity and support Pearson's assertion (folder 14) that the "advise, counsel, or doings" from any partial meeting of the Board of Overseers "in great and difficult cases, and in cases of non-agreement" cannot be taken as authoritative and that any final decisions require a general meeting of the Board of Overseers.
  - Extracts from records of the General Court relative to the organization of the Overseers of Harvard College in 1642, undated, UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 11
  - Extracts from records of General Court relative to Act forming Corporation in 1650, undated, UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 12
  - Extracts from Acts of 1642, 1650, and 1657, undated, UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 13
  - Extracts from Acts of 1642, 1650, and 1657, comments, undated, UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 14
  - Extracts from Harvard Corporation records relative to Hollis Professorship of Divinity from 1772 to 1792, undated, UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 15
- VI. Theses Theologica, first draft, [1805]; UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 16; (1 folder)
  Commencement Theses, Quaestiones, and Orders of Exercises, 1642-1818 (HUC 6642): this collection consists of Theses, Quaestiones, and Orders of Exercises for Commencement used in Harvard Commencement exercises from the 17th century into the early 19th century as precursors to the modern Commencement program.
  The themes discussed in this Theses Theologica focus on theology, the nature of God, the Holy Scriptures, the nature of truth and morals, and the relationship of men to God. The thesis is written in Latin.
- VII. Dr. Ware's course of reading for a student in divinity, 1808 September 2; UAI 15.955 Box 1, Folder 17; (1 folder)
  This reading list notes the required books, articles, and treatises on Biblical knowledge, the Scriptures, and natural and revealed religion for students in Henry Ware's divinity classes. The reading list notes the required treatises that discuss the doctrines and duties of revelation, ecclesiastical history, and pastoral office. The reading list also notes the recommended ministers whose sermons Ware wishes his students to consult. The list is addressed to Eliphalet Pearson.